Finding Aid for the P.M. Suski papers, ca. 1941-1961 LSC.2010.31
UCLA Library Special Collections
P.M. Suski papers
circa 1941-1961
UCLA Library Special Collections
Suski, P.M. (Peter Marie), b. 1875
LSC.2010.31
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Sakae Susuki was born in 1875. A native of Okayama Prefecture, he arrived in the United States in 1898. He graduated from the University of Southern California Medical School in 1917 with additional studies at Berlin University. He lived in San Francisco (1898-1906) but relocated to Los Angeles, California following the Great Earthquake. He was a photographer prior to Medical School and practiced medicine in Southern California before World War II and in Denver post-World War II. He was also known as Dr. Peter M. Suski. The collection consists primarily of manuscripts, clippings, and published versions of works by Sakae Susuki. Includes manuscripts of Issei Viewpoint, a series of short articles published in the English section of the Shin Nichibei (the Japanese American News) (1958-61) as well as clippings of the articles. Also includes clippings of other articles by and about Susuki, and manuscripts for his books, An Introduction to Shosho or the Grass Style of Writing, The Dictionary of Kanji, and Tenbunsh: Jsatsu. Additionally there is a small collection of pre-war photographs. Some materials in this collection are in Japanese.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942338383606533
Biography
Sakae Susuki was born in 1875; a native of Okayama Prefecture, he arrived in the United States in 1898; graduated University of Southern California Medical School, 1917; additional studies at Berlin University; lived in San Francisco (1898-1906) and relocated to Los Angeles, California following the Great Earthquake; was a photographer prior to Medical School; practiced medicine in Southern California before World War II and in Denver post-World War II; was also known as Dr. Peter M. Suski; he was also an author and a linguist; died 1961.
Scope and Content
Collection consists primarily of manuscripts, clippings, and published versions of works by Sakae Susuki. Includes manuscripts of Issei Viewpoint, a series of short articles published in the English section of the Shin Nichibei (the Japanese American News) (1958-61) as well as clippings of the articles. Also includes clippings of other articles by and about Susuki, and manuscripts for his books, An Introduction to Shosho or the Grass Style of Writing, The Dictionary of Kanji, and Tenbunsh: Jsatsu. Additionally there is a small collection of pre-war photographs.
Materials in this collection are in English and Japanese.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Published materials and manuscripts for his books and articles (Boxes 139 and 722).
Manuscripts for his books and articles and newspaper clippings (Box 140).
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Manuscripts for publication; Physicians -- United States -- Archives.; Authors -- Archives.; Photographs.; Japanese Americans -- United States -- Archives.; Suski, P.M. (Peter Marie), b. 1875--Archives.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles)
- Susuki Papers, ca. 1941-1961; 3.0 linear ft.
  - Published Materials and Manuscripts, 1.5 linear ft.
    Scope and Contents note
    For [Susuki Sakae's] books and articles.
    - Captain Henry Harkness, M.R.A.S., Ancient and Modern Alphabets of the Popular Hindu Languages, Southern Peninsula of India. London: Published for the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland by John W. Parker, West Strand, 1837., (1 item) (Box 139, Folder 1)
    - Peter M. Suski. "Ancient & Modern Alphabets of the Hindu and Related Languages of India, Tibet, Siam, etc.", (Manuscript, 38pp., 1 item) (Box 139, Folder 2)
    - A booklet, articles and papers written by Susuki Sakae., (6 items) (Box 139, Folder 3)
      - Hints to Students of the Japanese Language. Hollywood, California: W.M. Hawley., 1957; (12pp.) (Box 139, Folder 3)
      - "Beikoku umare Nihonjin-kei jid no taikaku chosa (Dai-ipp)" [characters] ["The body build of American-born Japanese children", Report No. 1], Tokyo Kenbikyo Gakkai Zasshi, vol. 39, no. 1., January 1932; (11pp.) (Box 139, Folder 3)
      - "Beikoku umare Nihonjin no taikaku (Daisamp)" [characters] ["The body build of American born Japanese", Report no. 3], Taiiku Kenkyu, vol. 5, nos. 5-6., April & June 1938; (40pp.) (Box 139, Folder 3)
      - "The Body Build of American-Born Japanese Children", Biometrika, vol. XXV, parts III & IV., December 1933; (pp. 323-352) (Box 139, Folder 3)
      - Historical Notes on Japan, Denver, Colorado., 1956; (Mimeographed. 21pp.) (Box 139, Folder 3)
      - Sword Making., n.d.; (3pp., mimeographed) (Box 139, Folder 3)
    - Manuscripts for his books. (Box 139, Folder 4-7)
      - Tenbunshu, Jsatsu [characters] [A Collection of Chinese Seal Characters, Volume I]., 1941; (Manuscript, 189pp., 1 volume). (Box 139, Folder 4)
      - Partial manuscripts for The Dictionary of Kanji with a chart of phonetic kana., n.d.; (45pp. + 31pp., 3 items) (Box 139, Folder 5)
      - 2 completed manuscripts for An Introduction to shosho or the grass style of writing., 1944; (118pp. + 118pp., 2 volumes) (Box 139, Folder 6-7)
    - Manuscript for Setsubun ni kansuru kenky [characters] [A study on the Chinese small seal characters]., n.d.; (98pp., 1 oversize bound volume) (Box 722)
  - Manuscripts, 0.5 linear ft.
    For his books and articles and newspaper clippings.
    - Manuscript for My life story (translation of Suiri Kaiko Gojunen [characters]., 1957; (53pp., 1 item) (Box 140, Folder 1)
    - Manuscripts for Issei Viewpoint., February 5, 1958-August 15, 1961; (199 items) (Box 140, Folder 2)
      A series of short articles Susuki Sakae published in the English section of the Shin Nichibei [characters] [The Japanese American News] in Los Angeles.
    - Clippings of his articles Issei Viewpoint (complete)., February 5, 1958-August 15, 1961; (1 notebook) (Box 140, Folder 3)
      Also includes a few other articles written by him or about him.
    - Engei [characters] [Synopsis of Japanese Shibai]., n.d.; (Manuscript, 45pp., 1 notebook) (Box 140, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous printed materials., (3 items) (Box 140, Folder 5)
    - Photographs., n.d. (postwar); (15 pieces) (Box 140, Folder 6)